Finding Aid for Ejner J. Jensen Papers, 1984-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ejner J. Jensen papers 1984-1997
Jensen, Ejner J.
1 linear foot
0509 Aa 2
Ejner Jensen was a professor in the Department of English at the University of Michigan, from 1964 to 2004. He was also active in faculty government. The majority of his papers focus on his involvement in university committees, especially the Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA).
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection was donated (donor # 9410 )in January 2004.
The collection is open without restriction.
Ejner Jensen was born January 28, 1937 in Omaha, Nebraska. He received his B.A. from Carlton College (Minnesota) in 1959, and his graduate education from Tulane University (New Orleans, Louisiana), receiving his M.A. in 1960 and Ph.D. in 1965. He began teaching at the University of Michigan English Department in 1964 as an instructor, and became a professor of English Language and Literature in 1979. He retired in 2004.
Throughout his career, Jensen actively participated in faculty government. He was a member of the Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA), and served as its vice-chair from 1991 to 1992 and chair from 1992 to 1993, as well as participating in or chairing several of its committees. He also served as Special Counsel to the President of the University of Michigan, working to improve administration and faculty relations, and as a member of many committees within the English Department and throughout the University.
The majority of The Ejner Jensen papers focus on his involvement in university committees, especially the Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA). The Ejner Jensen papers are divided into two series: Personal and University Committees.
Subjects:
Jensen, Ejner J.; Teacher participation in administration--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Senate. Advisory Committee on University Affairs.
- Personal
  Personal (0.1 linear feet, 1984-1996) includes biographical material on Jensen and copies of speeches he gave throughout his career. The biographical material covers his career through 1996. The speeches (1984-1996) are for commencement and honors convocation activities at the university, as well as English Literature topics. Also included are photocopies of photographs of six distinguished alumni of the University of Michigan English Department, and accompanying biographical information and a statement on their experience at the university.
  - Biographical (Box 1)
  - English Department Alumni (Box 1)
  - Speeches, 1984-1996 (Box 1)
- University Committees
  The bulk of the collection consists of the University Committees series (0.9 linear feet, 1989-1997). The papers include meeting minutes, memos and correspondence between committee members, drafts of reports, and Jensen's notes. Three committees are represented in this collection. The Organizational Task Force was charged with examining the structure of the university and suggesting improvements. The Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA) is the executive branch of faculty government. Most of the papers concern this committee. The Task Force on the Arts and Undergraduate Education worked to find ways to integrate the arts into undergraduate education.
  - Organizational Task Force, 1994-1996, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1993 (Box 1)
    - Department of Population Planning and International Health (PPHI), protesting cuts, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Freedom of Speech and Discriminatory Harassment, 1993-1996, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Committee Chair Retreats, 1990-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1990-1993, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - Role of Faculty Governance, 1993-1996 (Box 1)
    - Task Force on Faculty Retirement, 1989-1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Task Force on the Arts and Undergraduate Education, 1994-1997, 4 folders (Box 1)